Guide to the Frances Theresa and Frank B. Russell papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Frances Theresa and Frank B. Russell papers
1892-1936
SC0166
Russell, Frances Theresa, d. 1936.
1.5 Linear feet
Frances Russell's papers include: personal correspondence, manuscripts, course materials, notes, and photographs (1920-1936). Frank Russell's papers include: correspondence, manuscript material, documents, and photographs (1892-1903). The collection provides an overview of both individuals' careers.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Elizabeth Buckingham, 1977.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Associated Materials
Elizabeth Lee Buckingham Papers (SC0167)--Buckingham and Russell shared a house at 534 Lasuen Street.
Separated Materials
Letter from Lloyd Nolan to David Lamson regarding the problems in Nolan's budding acting career. 1930's. (removed to SC 103, Box 2)
Photograph of Frances Theresa Russell in front of a Stanford arch. (placed in photograph collection under "Faculty - Russell")
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Personal details on Frances Theresa Peet Russell and Frank B. Russell are sketchy. Mrs. Russell was graduated Phi Beta Kappa from the University of Iowa with a. Ph.B. degree in 1895. She taught in Iowa from 1895-1900, except for a year of graduate work at Radcliffe College in 1898-99. In 1900 she married Frank B. Russell, Hho died in 1903. In 1906 she came to Stanford as an Assistant in Philosophy during the period in William James gave his series of Stanford lectures. She remained as an Instructor in English, completing work on a Ph.D. degree at Columbia University in 1920. She attained the rank of Professor several years before her death from cancer on Feb. 15, 1936. Mrs. Russell was an authority on Robert Browning and published a number of articles and books on the Brownings, as well as on other subjects. She was also a published poet. She was co-author with Prof. Yvor Winters of the book The Case of David Lamson, published at Stanford in 1934 by the Lamson Defense Committee. A list of her publications can be found in Box 2, Folder 1.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Frank B. Russell was born in Fort Dodge, Iowa on Aug. 26, 1868. He received his Bachelors and Masters degrees from the University of Iowa in 1892 and 1895.(Prior to this he had spent two years alone in the Arctic doing anthropological and zoological work, which formed the basis for his book Explorations in the Far North, published in 1898.) In 1895 he went to Harvard, receiving an A.B. in 1896, an A.M. in 1897, and a Ph.D. in 1898. From 1896-1903 he was Instructor in Anthropology at Harvard. He was also an Ethnologist with the Bureau of American Ethnology from 1901-02. He died in 1903.
Description of the Collection
This group of papers which were separated out from the Elizabeth Buckingham Papers (SC 167), provide a very sketchy overview of two very respected careers. Mrs. Russell's papers include some personal correspondence, course materials, manuscripts, notes and unidentified photographs, all generally within the period 1920-33 with some material outside these dates by a few years. Mr. Russell's papers include material which Mrs. Russell evidently wanted to preserve after his death and kept until her own death - some correspondence and manuscript material, various documents of his academic career, and photographs relating to his work. This material falls within the period 1892-1903.
Access Terms
Buckingham, Elizabeth Lee, 1885-; Russell, Frances Theresa, d. 1936.; Russell, Frank B., 1868-1903.; Stanford University. Department of English. Faculty.; Photoprints.; San Francisco Earthquake and Fire, Calif., 1906
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - FRANCES T. RUSSELL - GENERAL FILES
    - Book of incidents., 1903-? (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes account of 1906 Earthquake.
    - Book of incidents., 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, personal., 1921-35 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, personal., 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Course and lecture notes, miscellaneous. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      May include Russel's own post-graduate study notes.
    - Essay writing - miscellaneous material, including notes., 1925, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript, "Journal kept during the summer of 1900." (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Handwritten, 118 pages. Account of the Russells' honeymoon trip to Arizona, during which Frank Russell pursued his archaeological explorations.
    - Manuscript, untitled, about the Bible. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Typewritten. 10 chapters, 156 pgs.
    - Manuscripts, drafts and notes of writings. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Manuscripts, drafts and notes of writings. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous material., 1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes list of Mrs. Russell's publications, 1905-34.
    - Photographs, miscellaneous unidentified. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Poetry - "Helen" poems and miscellaneous poems. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Publications. [Reprints], 1921-28 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Publications. [Some reprints], 1930-34 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Reviews and synopses. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Students listed by course. Master list: "Stanford students and friends, teachers and librarians." (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Writing. - miscellaneous material. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes notes and outlines.
  - FRANCES T. RUSSELL - COURSES
    - Browning - various courses., 1920's, 1930's (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Classical literature c40., 1932 Summer (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Criticism of recent literature, various courses., 1920's, 1930's (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Essay - various courses., 1920's, 1930's (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Essay - various courses., 1920's, 1930's (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Satire 202. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Utopian theme 97, 193, 197. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Victorian literature 185. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - FRANK B. RUSSELL
    - Correspondence, manuscripts and miscellaneous material., 1892-1903 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Photographs. Pertain to his anthropological work. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      May include one photo of him.
    - Photographs. Pertain to his anthropological work. (Box 3, Folder 8)
Major Correspondents and/or Items of Special Interest
In her early teaching years Mrs. Russell kept a "Book of Incidents" in which she recorded random thoughts and happenings. One of these includes her account of her experiences during and after the 1906 Earthquake (Box 1, Folder 1). In addition, her manuscript material and poetry in Boxes 1 & 2 are of special interest; most of this appears to be unpublished material.
It is helpful to know that Mrs. Russell always went by the name of Theresa or "Terri". In correspondence to her, "Peter" or "Betty" both are nicknames for Elizabeth Buckingham, with whom she shared a house until her death.